James H. Barnett Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
James H. Barnett Papers.
undated, 1907-1993.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
James H. Barnett, 1906-.
1.5 linear feet.
James Harwood Barnett was born in Owensboro, KY, on 9 October 1906. Barnett was employed by the University of Connecticut in 1935 as an instructor in Sociology. He specialized in the history of social thought and the sociology of art and literature. He attained full professorship in 1948 as was head of the Sociology Department from 1948 until 1962. Barnett directed the Honor's Program from 1967 until his retirement in 1970. A prolific author, Barnett has over thirty publications, including The American Christmas, a study in national culture published in 1954 and numerous biographies of campus notables.
MSS19970014
Biography
James Harwood Barnett was born in Owensboro, KY, on 9 October 1906. He attended Lindsey Wilson Junior College and Berea College, obtaining his A.B. degree in 1928. He was awarded a M.A. in 1930 from the University of Pennsylvania and a Ph.D. in 1939. He was a Harrison Fellow in Sociology at the University from 1933 until 1935.
Barnett was employed by the University of Connecticut in 1935 as an instructor in Sociology. He specialized in the history of social thought and the sociology of art and literature. He attained full professorship in 1948 as was head of the Sociology Department from 1948 until 1962. Barnett directed the Honor's Program from 1967 until his retirement in 1970. While at the University, Barnett served on numerous committees, including one which resulted in the establishment of the School of Social Work in 1946. He was a member of the University Senate for almost thirty years and was consistently reelected by his colleagues to the Senate Committee of Three, the guardian of academic tenure.
A prolific author, Barnett has over thirty publications, including The American Christmas, a study in national culture published in 1954 and numerous biographies of campus notables, such as Walter Stemmons, Professor I. G. Davis and former President Charles Beach. Barnett saw the purpose of these biographies as portraying “the unique value or contribution each made to his world as he knew it.”
Apart from his scholastic duties, Barnett participated in many civic activities. In 1943, he worked for the War Relocation Authority as a community analyst at a Japan ese relocation camp in Gila, Arizona. While on leave from the University from 1963 to 1965, he served as executive secretary to the Small Grants Committee of the National Institute of Mental Health. On the state level, Barnett was a member of the Board of Directors of the Connecticut Prison Association and the Board of Directors of Connecticut Children's Services. Locally, Barnett served on the Storrs Board of Education and was a member of the original Mansfield Town Council and a Justice of the Peace.
Scope and Content
The collection contains publications, speeches, notes, correspondence, articles, awards and photographs relating to Dr. Barnett's many activities.
Arrangement
Series I: Writings ( undated, 1907-1989 ) comprises the bulk of the collection and is arranged into three subseries: Publications, Unpublished speeches and papers, and Research Notes. Publications includes journal articles and reprints. Unpublished materials include eulogies and speeches commemorating various Storrs' personalities. Research notes contains handwritten notes, related publications, printed material and manuscript drafts.
Series II: Personal papers ( undated, 1928-1993 ) contains awards and degrees received by Dr. Barnett, biographical clippings, notes, family photographs and private correspondence. The University of Connecticut subseries documents Barnett's activities while at the University including subject files regarding campus unrest in the late 1960s and the I. G. Davis Memorial Fund.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Personal Papers.; Manuscripts.; Publications.
Occupations:
Educator.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Dr. Barnett began donating his materials to the Special Collections Department of the University of Connecticut Libraries following his retirement in 1970. These materials were transferred to the Historical Manuscripts and Archives Division in 1980. Additional papers were incorporated into the collection at various times since 1980. The Cynthia Snow letters were added in 1989.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Writings, undated, 1907-1989
  - Subseries A: Publications, undated, 1932-1989
    - Articles and Reprints
      - “College Seniors and the Liquor Problem”, 1932 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
      - “Personality in Primitive Society”, 1933 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
      - “Stimulating Student Activity”, 1936 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
      - “The Sociology of the Novel”, 1937 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
      - “Society and the Novel”, 1938 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
      - “Institutional Pressures and the Church”, 1938 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
      - “Social Organization and Social Structure”, 1942 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
      - “Christmas in American culture”, 1946 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
      - “Recent American Divorce Novels, 1938-1945”, 1948 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
      - “The Easter Festival”, 1949 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
      - “Research Areas in the Sociology of Art”, 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
      - “Changes in Student Attitudes”, 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
      - “The Sociology of Art”, 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
      - “The Importance of Art Publics”, 1960 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
      - “A Sociologist views the Arts”, 1961 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
      - “Sociological Aspects of the Literary System”, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
      - “Art is now what is consumed as art...”, 1980 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
      - “The American Christmas”, 1981 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - Books
      - The American Christmas, 1954, 1976 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
      - Divorce and the American Divorce Novel, 1858-1937, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
      - Divorce and the American Divorce Novel, 1858-1937, ca. 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - University of Connecticut history
      - Mr. Beach, 1960 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
      - Six Speeches of Walter Stemmons, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
      - “Prof”, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
      - Mr. Gentry, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
      - The Founding of the School of Social Work, 1980 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
      - Three Storrs Pioneers, 1981 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
      - Wilbur L. Cross Remembered, 1984 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
      - The Storrs Brothers and the Founding of the Storrs Agricultural School, 1881, 1982 (Box 1:, Folder 29)
      - Profiles, 1969-1982 (Box 1:, Folder 30)
      - A Storrs Memoir, 1935-1945, 1989 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
    - Mansfield Local history
      - Mansfield Historical Society, undated (Box 1:, Folder 32)
      - Chronology of Mansfield 1702-1972, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
      - On the Trail of a Legend, 1978 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
      - The Mansfield Poor House, 1985 (Box 1:, Folder 35)
  - Subseries B: Unpublished speeches and papers, undated, 1934-1985
    - A Study of Parole at Eastern State Penitentiary, 1934 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
    - Gila, Arizona Relocation report, 1943 (Box 1:, Folder 37)
    - The American Divorce novel, 1957 (Box 1:, Folder 38)
    - Sociology and the Fine Arts, 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 39)
    - Phi Beta Kappa speech, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 40)
    - Nathan Whetten speech, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 41)
    - G.A.L. Mehlquist speech, 1976 (Box 1:, Folder 42)
    - From Farm School to State University, undated (Box 1:, Folder 43)
    - The Storrs Brothers, 1981 (Box 1:, Folder 44)
    - Nathan L. Whetten eulogy, 1984 (Box 1:, Folder 45)
    - Albert Waugh eulogy, 1985 (Box 1:, Folder 46)
    - Chanel No. 5, undated (Box 1:, Folder 47)
  - Subseries C: Research notes, undated, 1907-
    - Divorce notes, undated (Box 2:, Folder 48)
    - Charles Beach Profile, 1907-1968 (Box 2:, Folder 49-54)
    - I.G. Davis Profile, 1967-1970 (Box 2:, Folder 55-56)
    - Charles Gentry Profile, 1930-1970 (Box 2:, Folder 57-58)
    - Holidays, undated (Box 2:, Folder 59-62)
    - Holidays, related articles
      - 1930s (Box 3:, Folder 63)
      - 1940s (Box 3:, Folder 64)
      - 1950-1955 (Box 3:, Folder 65)
      - 1956-1959 (Box 3:, Folder 66)
      - 1960s (Box 3:, Folder 67)
      - 1970s (Box 3:, Folder 68)
      - 1981 (Box 3:, Folder 69)
    - Christmas (Box 3:, Folder 70)
    - Walter Stemmons Profile, 1943-1981 (Box 3:, Folder 71)
    - The Storrs Brothers, undated (Box 3:, Folder 72)
    - Three Storrs Pioneers, undated (Box 3:, Folder 73)
    - Koons (Box 3:, Folder 74-75)
    - Torrey (Box 3:, Folder 76-77)
    - Whitney (Box 3:, Folder 78-79)
    - Mansfield Poor House (Box 3:, Folder 80)
- Series II: Personal papers, undated, 1928-1993
  - Awards, Degrees and resolutions
    - Berea College, 1928 (Box 4:, Folder 81)
    - University of Pennsylvania, 1930 (Box 4:, Folder 82)
    - Memberships, 1932-1959 (Box 4:, Folder 83)
    - University of Connecticut, 1970 (Box 4:, Folder 84-85)
    - Mansfield, CT, 1973 (Box 4:, Folder 86)
  - Berea College yearbook, 1928 (Box 4:, Folder 87)
  - Genealogy research notes, undated (Box 4:, Folder 88)
  - Family genealogy, undated (Box 4:, Folder 89)
  - Family genealogy—William Barnett, undated (Box 4:, Folder 90)
  - Family genealogy—Palmer-Bristow, undated (Box 4:, Folder 91)
  - Family photographs, undated (Box 4:, Folder 92)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 4:, Folder 93)
  - Biographical clippings, 1969-1985 (Box 4:, Folder 94)
  - Biographical notes, undated (Box 4:, Folder 95)
  - Personal letters, 1961-1989 (Box 4:, Folder 96)
  - Correspondence—General, 1954-1982 (Box 4:, Folder 97)
  - Correspondence—Beach profile, 1954-1982 (Box 4:, Folder 98)
  - Correspondence—Davis profile, 1971 (Box 4:, Folder 99)
  - Correspondence—Stemmons profile, 1971 (Box 4:, Folder 100)
  - Cynthia Snow letters, 1984-1989 (Box 4:, Folder 101)
  - Vacation report, 1935 (Box 4:, Folder 102)
  - Agreement—The Macmillan Company, 1953 (Box 4:, Folder 103)
  - Folklore, undated (Box 4:, Folder 104)
  - Privacy, undated (Box 4:, Folder 105-106)
  - Althea Stadtler, undated (Box 4:, Folder 107)
  - Jacqueline Kennedy photograph, ca. 1963 (Box 4:, Folder 108)
  - History of Separatist Church, 1977 (Box 4:, Folder 109)
  - Log of Virgin Island Cruise, 1982 (Box 4:, Folder 110)
  - Gravestones, 1974-1993 (Box 4:, Folder 111)
  - Museum articles, 1984 (Box 4:, Folder 112)
  - Notes, Annual reports, undated (Box 4:, Folder 113)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 4:, Folder 114)
  - Mansfield, undated (Box 4:, Folder 115-116)
  - Mansfield Road naming, undated (Box 4:, Folder 117)
  - Subseries A: University of Connecticut, undated, 1939-1981
    - Personal drafts and articles, undated (Box 4:, Folder 118)
    - UConn history, undated (Box 4:, Folder 119)
    - “Fund for the Advancement of Education”, 1956 (Box 4:, Folder 120-122)
    - Campus unrest—“The Continuing Crisis at Uconn A White paper”, 1968 (Box 4:, Folder 123-124)
    - I. G. Davis Memorial Fund, 1939-1940 (Box 4:, Folder 125)
    - Basic genealogy, 1970 (Box 4:, Folder 126)
    - Nathan Whetten Reception, 1981 (Box 4:, Folder 127)